It’s crazy when you think about all of
the different kinds of foods we eat.
We just swallow and hope
it all works out for the best.
Well, as it turns out,
there are better ways to think about keeping
our bodies humming healthfully along.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
In this episode,
we look at ways to change our diet
for the good of the whole planet.
In our first story,
the EAT-Lancet Commission
lays out the best diet
for human and planetary health.
Scientists have a clear moral
obligation to clearly warn humanity
of any catastrophic threat
and to tell it like it is.
In November 2019, more than
11,000 scientists from 150 countries
clearly and unequivocally
declared that planet Earth
is facing a climate emergency.
CO2 levels are rising, the glaciers
are melting, Antarctica is melting.
The oceans are getting
hotter, more acidic.
Sea levels are rising, and so
are extreme weather events.
And yes, fossil fuel use is
going up, like air travel, but
so is per capita meat consumption.
In fact, one of the solutions
they offer to help the climate
crisis is eating mostly
plant-based foods while reducing the
global consumption of animal products.
And what makes designing a sustainable
diet so easy is that the same advice—
like eat less meat—is good for
both personal health, like reducing
the risk of our number #1 killer,
as well as for planetary health.
The least healthy foods also cause
the worst environmental impact.
The foods with the most nutrition
just so happen to be the foods
that cause the lowest greenhouse gas
emissions, so you get this win-win effect.
So let's put it all together.
If we are to redesign the global food
system for human and planetary health—
which is to say human health and future
human health—what would it look like?
Enter: the EAT-Lancet Commission,
the result of more than two years
of collaboration between 37 experts
from 16 countries, suggesting
a cut in total meat consumption
down to like an ounce a day—
that's like the weight of
a single chicken nugget—
all the while dramatically
increasing our intakes
of legumes—which are beans,
split peas, chickpeas, and lentils—
nuts, fruits, and vegetables,
because we're not just in a
climate crisis, but a health crisis.
Unhealthy diets cause more death
and disease than smoking,
more than unsafe sex, and alcohol,
drug, and tobacco use combined.
But we can address both
crises at the same time
by increasing our consumption
of whole plant foods
and substantially reducing our
consumption of animal source foods.
Eating such a diet could save the lives
of more than 10 million people a year
and may just help save the world.
The Paris Agreement had set
out a boundary condition,
an aspirational goal for a carbon budget
to help prevent catastrophic impacts,
and staying within the
boundary for climate change
can be achieved by consuming
plant-based diets.
And the personal benefits may be
comparable with or even exceed
the value of the environmental benefits.
The healthcare benefits alone
for a healthy global diet—
a predominantly plant-based diet,
a vegetarian or a vegan diet—
could exceed the price
of the carbon saved.
We're talking up to $30
trillion dollars a year saved
from the health benefits alone.
Now if the health of yourself,
the planet, and your own children
doesn't quite motivate you, consider
that you may also be facing threats
to the global beer supply.
And healthier diets don't just
reduce greenhouse gas emissions.
Since livestock production is the
single largest driver of habitat loss,
reducing meat consumption
is also the key
to biodiversity conservation,
ideally, perhaps, reducing demand
for animal-based
foods by increasing
the proportion of plant-based
foods up to like 90% of the diet.
Livestock production is also a
leading cause of soil loss, water
and nutrient pollution. Yet it appears
to be a blind spot in water policy.
Despite the fact that animal products
form the single most important factor
in humanity's water footprint,
water managers never seem
to talk about meat and dairy.
But it's not just animal products.
I mean, yes, at least 80% of
the deforestation in the Amazon
is to raise cattle and grow
feed crops like soybeans
to export to other farm animals,
but also to make vegetable oil,
most of which is from palm and soy.
Both crops have been expanding,
resulting in massive deforestation.
It just seems particularly egregious
if that deforestation takes place
for the sake of junk food.
Not everyone agrees we should
be moving to healthier diets, though.
The World Health Organization actually
pulled out of the EAT-Lancet Commission
because of their promotion of a global
move to more plant-based foods.
See, if we focused on promoting
predominantly plant-based foods
and excluding foods deemed
unhealthy, including meat and other
animal-based foods, such a diet could,
yeah, save 10 million lives a year,
$30 trillion dollars, and help save
the entire planet, but could lead
to the loss of jobs linked to animal
husbandry and the production of junk.
In our next story,
we look at the purported
decline of nutrients in our crops
due to soil degradation,
or is that just supplement
industry propaganda?
Internet articles
and the popular press
frequently state that
the mineral nutrient
composition of crops
has been declining
over the last 50 years
with titles like
"The great nutrient collapse,"
blamed in part on the purported
nutrient depletion of the soil.
This narrative is touted
by the leading
dietary supplement
trade association,
but is it true?
This is probably
the most cited study,
comparing the nutrient content
of U.S. fruits and vegetables
between 1950 and 1999,
and about half,
seven of the 13
nutrients tested,
showed no significant decline,
and the six that did
only declined by about
15 percent on average.
A similar study in the UK
looking at mineral content
had similar findings
with declines in about half.
Of course, the drop in sodium
doesn't matter;
we get too much of it as it is,
and most people
get more than enough copper.
But the ten percent drop
in magnesium is significant,
and though the drop in iron
looks precipitous,
the absolute drop is tiny,
since fruits and veggies
have so little to begin with.
Australian researchers
had similar findings:
a halving of iron in fruit
over the last few decades,
but the absolute drop
is like 0.2 mg per serving,
which is about 1/50th
of the recommended
daily allowance for most people,
and the same with zinc.
And there was actually
an increase in grains.
As you can see, there was just
a few milligrams difference
in calcium or magnesium,
where the RDA is in
the hundreds of milligrams.
So, with such small
absolute differences,
any true decrease
in mineral content
is unlikely
to have a large impact
on nutritional intake.
And it's not clear
if these changes are even real.
These comparisons of historical
food composition tables
are not a reliable way
to determine changes
in nutrient composition
of foods over time,
since they are just
unmatched snapshots in time
not meant to sync up.
So, these may have been
different varieties,
or there may have been
differences
in ripeness, season, location.
If you look at
the levels of minerals
in the soil itself,
you don't tend
to see declining levels,
and in some cases,
you actually see
a significant rise
in mineral levels
nearly across the board
over the last half century.
So, where is this gloomy
supplement industry propaganda
coming from?
There's been a concern
that rising CO2 levels
might reduce nutrients in crops,
but the largest recorded change
was a 59 percent increase
in total antioxidant content,
thanks to higher
phytonutrient levels.
What about the concern
that modern varieties
grow so much larger and faster,
potentially creating a trade-off
between yield
and nutrient concentration?
One way to study this
is to grow a whole bunch
of different varieties
released over the years
under the same conditions,
which is what these researchers
did with broccoli.
14 cultivars
released over 50 years,
and they found that there was
no clear change over time
in mineral content,
though they did find
that larger heads of broccoli
did tend to have
lower mineral content;
something to keep in mind
next time you shop.
As for the dietary supplement
trade association's claim
that Americans don't get the
nutrients they need from foods?
Well, for example,
only half of Americans
reach even 75 mg
of vitamin C a day--
less than the amount
in a single orange.
So, why aren't Americans
getting enough fruit
and vegetable nutrients?
Because they aren't eating
enough fruits and vegetables.
They don't need pills,
they just need produce.
So, even if there really is
15 percent less vitamin C
in today's broccoli,
that just may mean
you have to eat
six florets of today's broccoli
instead of five florets
from yesteryear.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
As always, all proceeds from
book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.